Ledger Lens turns an auditable transaction ledger into explainable historical risk metrics.
It is a public engineering demo, not a trading terminal: it does not predict prices, automate trades, or provide investment advice. The offline demo stays available when providers fail.
The system is a modular monolith. A Next.js BFF keeps the access token inside an HttpOnly cookie.
FastAPI coordinates owner-scoped use cases, PostgreSQL stores precise Decimal values, and Redis handles market-data caching and fixed-window rate limits.
Financial calculations stay deterministic; an optional language model can only explain their output.
Here I register with synthetic information and automatically enter an authenticated session. I create a US-dollar portfolio,
then record a cash deposit and an Apple purchase. Each transaction has a stable idempotency reference, so retrying a failed submission cannot double-post the ledger.
The backend validates quantities, prices, fees, funding, and ownership. Another user receives the same not-found response as a genuinely missing portfolio.
Money stays Decimal through domain boundaries and PostgreSQL NUMERIC in storage, while statistical conversions are explicit, local, and covered by tolerance tests.
The browser never reads or stores the API token.
Analytics runs only after I choose a date range. The response includes simple return, annualized volatility, maximum drawdown, and the historical Sharpe ratio.
The allocation chart combines latest security values with cash. Every result carries an as-of date, a stale flag, and provider provenance.
I can open methodology to inspect adjusted close, simple daily returns, 252-period annualization, the dated illustrative risk-free rate, cash-flow treatment, fees, timezone, and no-look-ahead alignment.
Risk summaries are generated only when I request them. The language model never calculates metrics, assigns authority, or changes the risk level.
With no DeepSeek key in the public deployment, deterministic risk rules return a bounded explanation, limitations, disclaimer, generator, prompt version, and a persisted historical snapshot.
Security is enforced at both layers: HttpOnly sessions in the BFF, owner checks in application services, Argon2 passwords, and HMAC-hashed rate-limit identifiers.
Transactions are idempotent. CI tests database migrations, PostgreSQL, Redis, offline financial edge cases, container startup, and cache behavior. The latest quality workflow passes.
This product explains historical behavior; it does not forecast prices or recommend trades. The live demo, source code, architecture notes, release, and three-minute video are linked from GitHub.